<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          Utrum anima cogitativa possit cognoscere substantias materiales
        </title>
        <author>Jean de Jandun (Ioannes de Ianduno)</author>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Paolo Rubini</persName>
          <resp>Encoding and transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.1">
          <date when="2017-06-20"/>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Paolo Rubini (University of Helsinki)</publisher>
        <authority>
          <ref target="http://blogs.helsinki.fi/rationality-in-perception/">
            Rationality in Perception: Transformations of Mind and Cognition
            1250-1550. Research project financed by the European Research
            Council under the grant agreement n. 637747
          </ref>
        </authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref
          target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
          Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Ve_1544">
            Ioannis Iandoni Super tres libros De anima quaestiones
            subtilissimae. Cum annotationibus textuum et quotationibus
            commentariorum, ea cura nuper emendatae, ut castigatiores nunquam
            prodierint, Venetiis: apud Iuntas, 1544, col. 68va--b
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0"
                 url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/1.0/critical.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2017-06-20" status="draft" n="0.0.1">
          <p>Created the file for the first time</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" type="translation">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#Ve_1544" n="68-v"/><cb ed="#Ve_1544" n="a"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="da-28-l3q21">
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-01">
          Because of something which was previously said one can ask:
          Is the cogitative soul able to cognize material substances?
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-02">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">1<hi
          rendition="simple:superscript">st</hi> arg.</hi></supplied> First, one
          can argue for the affirmative answer on account of what <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> sais in book II of his <title>De
          anima</title>: When a sense apprehends its proper objects, along with
          them it also apprehends individual intentions of different kinds
          according to genera and species; i.e., it apprehends the intention of
          this individual human being and the intention of this individual
          horse. But it is well known that this individual human being is a
          substance, and this individual horse <supplied>is a substance;
          and</supplied> likewise about other <supplied>individual
          things</supplied>. Under “sense”, <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> <supplied>in his sentence</supplied>
          understands either a particular sense <supplied>like sight, hearing
          etc.</supplied> or the cogitative power, which is a power of the
          sensitive soul. If he understands a particular sense, then
          <supplied>we have to assume that</supplied> the cogitative soul, which
          is a more noble and more perfect power <supplied>than any particular
          sense</supplied>, will even stronger cognize objects of this kind
          <supplied>= individual material substances</supplied>. If he
          <supplied>under “sense”</supplied> understands the cogitative soul,
          then we have immediately got the point. Therefore etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-03">
          And in the following comment <name ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name>
          says that it belongs accidentally to the senses to apprehend
          differences – in particular substantial differences – among
          individuals, insofar as they are individuals; this belongs to the
          senses not insofar as they are just senses, but insofar as they are
          human senses. For it manifestly belongs to human senses to apprehend
          individual intentions of substances that are considered by the
          intellect. Therefore etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-04">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">2<hi
          rendition="simple:superscript">nd</hi> arg.</hi></supplied> Moreover,
          if the cogitative power did not cognize a material substance, then the
          intellect could not cognize it either, which is nonsense
          <supplied>because the intellect’s proper function is to cognize any
          material substance</supplied>. The inference can be proved as follows:
          an act of the cogitative power is necessary in order to have an act of
          intellection, in particular when the objects of acts of intellection
          are material things; this is evident from what is said <supplied>by
          <name ref="#Aristotle">Aristotle</name></supplied> in <title>De anima</title> III: <hi
          rendition="simple:italic">for whoever is understanding, it is
          necessary to consider some phantasm</hi>. Therefore etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-05">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">To the opposite</hi></supplied>
          One can argue for the opposite view: if the cogitative soul cognized
          material forms, then for the same reason the cogitative soul would
          cognize itself, since the cogitative soul is a material substance or
          form, as it is manifest from what was said previously. This, however,
          appears to be impossible, for a material and corporeal form can never
          reflect about itself, as it is commonly assumed by reference to the
          <title>Liber de causis</title>. For this reason etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-06">
          This reason is confirmed by the following argument: the cogitative
          soul is naturally apt to cognize actual beings only by means of their
          proper species. For there is no reason for which the cogitative soul
          should cognize one being by means of its proper species and another
          being without its proper species. But the cogitative soul cannot
          receive the proper species of itself, otherwise one and the same
          subject – i.e. the human body – would have the very same
          <supplied>form</supplied> both according to <supplied>the
          form’s</supplied> real being and according to <supplied>the
          form’s</supplied> spiritual being; but this is impossible. For this
          reason etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-07">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">Response:</hi></supplied> On
          this topic there are two probable opinions. <supplied>1.</supplied>
          The first opinion is that the human cogitative soul only cognizes
          material substances in themselves and formally, if it <supplied>= the
          cogitative soul</supplied> receives their proper species; for the
          cogitative soul can only cognize something properly and in itself and
          formally, if it <supplied>= the cogitative soul</supplied> receives
          the proper species of it. This assumption is supposed to be manifest.
          But the cogitative soul cannot receive the proper species of any
          material substance. For this species has to be a substance in a way,
          as it has been said previously, and the cogitative soul cannot receive
          in itself anything belonging to the genus of substance, since it
          <supplied>= the cogitative soul</supplied> is
          <supplied>itself</supplied> a <supplied>substantial</supplied> form
          and act. For this reason etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-08">
          One could say, however, that the cogitative soul indeed cognizes
          individual properties that exist in a material substance and are not
          apprehended by any particular sense. These properties are called
          non-sensible intentions, and they are what <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> calls intentions of individual
          substances: such as, for instance, this goodness, this malice, this
          fatherhood, this being-son/daughter, this action, this passion, and
          similar properties that belong to other categories and which are
          neither common nor proper sensible objects; these properties cannot be
          apprehended by particular senses. But the cogitative soul cognizes
          intentions of this kind, as all philosophers who have spoken about the
          difference between the powers of the human soul – in particular <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name>, <name>Albert</name>,
          <name>Avicenna</name>, <name>Algazel</name> – testify. And this can
          also be proved sufficiently by the following argument: since the
          cogitative power is as a cognitive power nobler and more excellent
          than any particular sense and the common sense, it <supplied>=the
          cogitative power</supplied> must cognize things that cannot be
          cognized by these latter powers, and such things can only be
          intentions of the kind I have mentioned. For this reason
          <supplied>etc.</supplied>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-09">
          This view can be confirmed according to the intention of <name
          ref="#Aristotle">Aristotle</name> and <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name>. For it is known that the human soul,
          <cb ed="#Ve_1544" n="b"/>
          which inheres in the human body, is nobler than any other inherent
          <supplied>= bodily</supplied> soul und must have a power that is
          nobler than any powers of other animals. That power can only be the
          cogitative power, which reasons about particular things that have been
          apprehended. Therefore it is called a certain reason, according to
          <supplied>what</supplied> <name ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name>
          <supplied>says</supplied> in this third book of his <title>De
          anima</title>. For this reason etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-10">
          <supplied>2.</supplied> The second opinion could be that the
          cogitative power cognizes material substances by means of their
          individual proper species, but <supplied>only</supplied> insofar as
          the species of this kind that are received in the cogitative soul do
          not belong to the category of substance, but to the category of
          accident, for instance to the category of quality; these species
          nonetheless represent material substances to the extent that they are
          proper effects of them. And it does not appear to be inconvenient that
          a material substance immediately produces some spiritual accident
          <supplied>= quality</supplied> in a subject that is naturally apt
          <supplied>to receive it</supplied>, when the proximate agent is
          together with the patient, as it is evident from
          <title>Physics</title> VII. But a material substance is not together
          with the human cogitative soul in the way a stone, a piece of wood and
          things of this kind are; <supplied>for this reason</supplied> we will
          have to admit that a material substance of this kind produces its
          species in the medium existing between the cogitative soul and the
          material substance, and through this medium it <supplied>= the
          material substance</supplied> produces <supplied>its
          species</supplied> in the organ of the senses and further on in the
          cogitative soul. But from this it does not follow that the particular
          senses cognize the material substance, for they are not appointed to
          cognize it by itself, nor do they receive the species of the substance
          according to spiritual being, as it is required for cognition. Oh
          might I know what is true in this question! If some new ideas appear
          to my mind, I will write them down at another place.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-11">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">To the 1<hi
          rendition="simple:superscript">st</hi> argument:</hi></supplied> Both
          reasons and authorities in favor of both opinions can be avoided
          according to what we have just said. Thus, when <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> says that the sense apprehends the
          individual intention of this human being and of this horse,
          <supplied>we can reply that</supplied> under “individual intention” he
          does not understands the very substantial form of the human being or
          of the horse, but some non-sensible property which belongs to such an
          individual, so that <supplied>the sense = the cogitative
          power</supplied> would cognize this paternity, this
          being-son/being-daughter, this capacity of laughing, this bodily
          strength, this aptitude to walk <supplied>etc.</supplied>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-12">
          Likewise, when <name ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> says that it
          belongs accidentally to the senses to apprehend the substantial
          differences of individuals, <supplied>we can reply that</supplied>
          under “substantial differences” he understands some non-sensible
          properties deriving from the substance of an individual; <name
          ref="#Averroes">Averroes</name> also calls them individual intentions
          of the substances considered by the intellect.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-13">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">To the 2<hi
          rendition="simple:superscript">nd</hi> argument:</hi></supplied> To
          the second argument – which was a reason argument, not an authority
          argument – we can reply as follows: in order for the intellect to
          cognize material substances it suffices that the cogitative power
          cognizes them by their proper accidents, particularly by operations
          which belong to them <supplied>= material substances</supplied> as
          proper accidents per se. Likewise, in order <supplied>for the
          intellect</supplied> to understand immaterial substances it is not
          necessary that the cogitative power cognizes them – this is even
          impossible, since a material and organic power is absolutely not able
          to cognize any spiritual and incorporeal thing –, but it suffices that
          the cogitative power apprehends proper effects of them <supplied>=
          immaterial substances</supplied>, i.e. the perpetual and uniform
          motions <supplied>of the stars</supplied>, as it is evident from
          <title>Physics</title> VIII. For this reason, etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-14">
          <supplied><hi rendition="simple:bold">To the “to the
          opposite”:</hi></supplied> The argument “to the opposite” – namely
          that the cogitative soul, for the very same reason <supplied>for which
          it would cognize material substances</supplied>, should also cognize
          itself – is very complicate and not very fine. Nonetheless we may
          reply that the cogitative soul does not cognize itself by itself or
          through its proper species, whether this species is taken to belong to
          the category of substance or to a category of accidents. But if the
          cogitative soul cognizes itself <supplied>at all</supplied>, then this
          is so only by its operation, since the cogitative
          <supplied>soul</supplied> knows that it is cogitating, which is its
          proper and intrinsic activity. Thus, the cogitative soul perhaps does
          not cognize its own operation, for it is an organic and corporeal
          power; but it is the intellect that cognizes it <supplied>= the
          operation of the cogitative power</supplied>, and human beings
          <supplied>in turn cognizes this operation</supplied> by means of the
          intellect. If someone said that she is aware of her cogitating and she
          knows her cogitating, then we might reply to her that she is abusing
          her cogitating; in fact she should say that the intellect
          <supplied>and not the cogitative power</supplied> understands her
          cogitating.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-28-l3q21-1544en-15">
          I do not know anything more about this topic. Thus, try to think
          yourself, too. And so on.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
